Moritz Böhle

PHD STUDENT · MAX PLANCK INSTITUTE FOR INFORMATICS

■ moritzboehle@me.com | • moboehle | • moritz-boehle

Research statement

My research is focused on interpretable, trustworthy, and responsible deep learning. In particular, over the course of my PhD, I investigated how to design *inherently interpretable* deep neural networks such as the CoDA and the B-cos Networks, which are optimised to inherently provide explanations that highlight important input features.

Education _____

Kyutai, open science AI lab

Paris

POST DOC POSITION

06/2024 - present

Max Planck Institute for Informatics

Saarbrücken

PHD IN INTERPRETABILITY IN DEEP LEARNING, SUMMA CUM LAUDE

03/2019 - 05/2024

Advisors: Prof. Dr. Bernt Schiele, Prof. Dr. Mario Fritz

D 1:

Bernstein Center for Computational Neuroscience

Berlin

MSc Computational Neuroscience, GPA 1.0 (Best possible: 1.0)

10/2016 - 01/2019

Machine Learning · Models of Higher Brain Functions · Models of Neural Systems

Thesis: Noise Suppression and Speech Enhancement using Deep Learning. Grade: 1.0 (Best possible: 1.0)

University of California, Santa Cruz

Santa Cruz, CA, USA

UC EDUCATION ABROAD PROGRAM, GPA 4.0 (BEST POSSIBLE: 4.0)

10/2014 - 06/2015

Programming in Java, C, C++ · Biophysics

Freie Universität Berlin

Berlin

BSc Physics, GPA 1.0 (Best possible: 1.0)

01/2012 - 08/2016

Linear Algebra · Analysis · Analytical Mechanics · Statistical Physics

Thesis: Evaluating different barrier-crossing theories using Langevin simulations. Grade: 1.0 (Best possible: 1.0)

Research and Publications _____

(* EQUAL CONTRIBUTION)

- 2024 S. Arya*, S. Rao*, **M. Böhle***, B. Schiele. *B-cosification: Transforming Deep Neural Networks to be Inherently Interpretable.* arxiv:2411.00715. The European Conference on Computer Vision (NeurIPS), 2024.
- S. Mahajan*, S. Rao*, **M. Böhle**, B. Schiele. *Discover-then-name: Task-agnostic Concept Bottlenecks via Automated Concept Discovery.* arxiv:2407.14499. The European Conference on Computer Vision (ECCV), 2024.
- A. Parchami-Araghi*, **M. Böhle***, S. Rao*, B. Schiele. *Good Teachers Explain: Explanation-Enhanced Knowledge Distillation.* arxiv:2402.03119v2. The European Conference on Computer Vision (ECCV), 2024.
- 2023 **M. Böhle**, N. Singh, M. Fritz, B. Schiele. *B-cos Alignment for Inherently Interpretable CNNs and Vision Transformers.* Accepted for publication at IEEE Transactions on Pattern Analysis and Machine Intelligence (TPAMI), 2024.
- S. Rao, **M. Böhle**, B. Schiele. *Better Understanding Differences in Attribution Methods via Systematic Evaluations.* Accepted for publication at IEEE Transactions on Pattern Analysis and Machine Intelligence (TPAMI), 2024.
- S. Rao*, **M. Böhle***, A. Parchami-Araghi, B. Schiele. *Studying How to Efficiently and Effectively Guide Models with Explanations*. International Conference on Computer Vision (ICCV), 2023.
- A. Kukleva*, **M. Böhle***, B. Schiele, H. Kuehne, C. Rupprecht. *Temperature Schedules for self-supervised contrastive methods on long-tail data*. International Conference on Learning Representations (ICLR), 2023.
- 2022 **M. Böhle**, M. Fritz, B. Schiele. *B-cos Networks: Alignment is All We Need for Interpretability.* Conference on Computer Vision and Patter Recognition (CVPR), 2022.

- S. Rao, **M. Böhle**, B. Schiele. *Towards Better Understanding Attribution Methods*. Conference on Computer Vision and Patter Recognition (CVPR), 2022.
- 2022 **M. Böhle**, M. Fritz, B. Schiele. *Optimising for Interpretability: Convolutional Dynamic Alignment Networks.* IEEE Transactions on Pattern Analysis and Machine Intelligence (TPAMI), 2022.
- **M. Böhle**, M. Fritz, B. Schiele. *Convolutional Dynamic Alignment Networks for Interpretable Classifications*. Conference on Computer Vision and Patter Recognition (CVPR), oral, 2021.
- 2019 **M. Böhle***, F. Eitel*, M. Weygandt, K. Ritter. *Layerwise Relevance Propagation for Explaining DNN Decisions in MRI-based Alzheimer's Disease Classification*. **Frontiers in Aging Neuroscience** 11 (2019): 194.
- J. Kappler, J. O. Daldrop, F. Brüning, **M. Böhle**, R. Netz. *Memory-induced acceleration and slowdown of barrier crossing*. **The Journal of Chemical Physics** 148.1 (2018).

Professional Experience _____

05/2018 - 12/2018 Deer	Learning Research	. Master's student	Audatic GmbH.	Berlin
-------------------------------	-------------------	--------------------	---------------	--------

10/2017 - 05/2018 Software Development Digital Unit Volkswagen Financial Services AG, Berlin
01/2012 - 10/2012 Software Development and Quality Management Tembit Software GmbH

Academic Activities ___

06/2023 - present	Co-supervision MSc thesis Collaboration with S. Arya, S. Rao, B. Schiele.
	Increasing the interpretability of conventional Deep Neural Networks

05/2021 - 10/2021 Co-supervision BSc thesis Collaboration with N. Singh, D. Stutz, B. Schiele.

Exploring the relationship between robustness and interpretability

04/2020 - 03/2021 **Teaching Assistant** Elements of Data Science and Artificial Intelligence, B. Schiele.

03/2019 - present Reviewing activities IEEE PAMI, CVPR, ECCV, ICLR, NeurIPS, IEEE Trans. Inf. Forensics Secur., ICML

10/2015 - 09/2016 **Teaching Assistant** Linear Algebra and Analysis, R. Klein

Invited Talks_

03/2023 Spotlight @ Explainability in Machine Learning Workshop, Tübingen.

Towards B-cos Deep Neural Networks as the new default

06/2022 Spotlight @ XAI for Computer Vision (XAI4CV) workshop, CVPR.

B-cos Networks: Alignment is All We Need for Interpretability

12/2021 Invited talk @ Massachusetts Institute of Technology (MIT).

B-cos Networks: Alignment is All We Need for Interpretability

Scholarships, Awards, Grants _____

10/2022 Outstanding Reviewer ECCV 2022

01/2015 - 03/2019 Full scholarship German Academic Scholarship Foundation (Studienstiftung des Deutschen Volkes)

10/2014 - 12/2014 Sudy abroad scholarship DAAD PROMOS program

Travel grant Fulbright program

Extra-curricular activities ___

05/2021 - 01/2024 PhD student representative Computer Vision and Machine Learning department, MPI for Informatics

04/2017 - 01/2019 MSc student representative Bernstein Center for Computational Neuroscience